You must be puzzled by the fact that some teens do well in school, lead clubs and teams and volunteer in their communities, but they eat Tide Pods for an online challenge, speed and text while driving, binge drink and experiment with illicit drugs. How can so many teens be so smart, skilled and responsible -- and careless risk-takers at the same time? When I was 16, while frequently observing my peers in person as well as on social media, I began to wonder why so many teens took such crazy risks. It seems like getting a certificate from DARE class in the fifth grade can't stop them. (Laughter) What was even more alarming to me was that the more they exposed themselves to these harmful risks, the easier it became for them to continue taking risks. Now this confused me, but it also made me incredibly curious. So, as someone with a name that literally means "to explore knowledge," I started searching for a scientific explanation. Now, it's no secret that teens ages 13 to 18 are more prone to risk-taking than children or adults, but what makes them so daring? Do they suddenly become reckless, or is this just a natural phase that they're going through? Well neuroscientists have already found evidence that the teen brain is still in the process of maturation -- and that this makes them exceptionally poor at decision-making, causing them to fall prey to risky behaviors. But in that case, if the maturing brain is to blame, then why are teens more vulnerable than children, even though their brains are more developed than those of children? Also, not all teens in the world take risks at the same level. Are there some other underlying or unintentional causes
Es sorprendente que algunos sean buenos estudiantes, lideren clubes y equipos e incluso sean voluntarios en sus comunidades, pero comen detergente por un reto viral, usan el celular mientras conducen y exceden la velocidad se emborrachan y prueban drogas ilegales. ¿Cómo pueden tantos adolescentes ser tan hábiles, inteligentes y responsables y, al mismo tiempo, tan descuidados y correr tantos riesgos? Cuando tenía 16 años, solía observar a mis compañeros, tanto en persona como en las redes sociales, y comencé a preguntarme por qué los jóvenes corrían tantos riesgos. Parece que obtener un certificado del curso de lucha contra las drogas no puede detenerlos. (Risas) Lo que más me llamaba la atención era que cuanto más se exponían a estos riesgos perjudiciales, les era más fácil correr más riesgos. Esto me confundía, pero también me generó mucha curiosidad. Como alguien cuyo nombre significa literalmente "explorar el conocimiento", comencé a buscar una explicación científica. Todos sabemos que los adolescentes de entre 13 y 18 años tienden a correr más riesgos que los niños o los adultos, pero ¿qué los hace tan atrevidos? ¿Se vuelven imprudentes repentinamente? ¿O están atravesando una etapa natural? Los neurocientíficos ya han encontrado pruebas de que el cerebro adolescente todavía no ha madurado y esto hace que no sean nada buenos al tomar decisiones, y que sean presas fáciles de conductas riesgosas. Pero, si la culpa es del cerebro que no ha madurado, ¿por qué los jóvenes son más vulnerables que los niños, si sus cerebros están más desarrollados? Además, no todos los adolescentes del mundo toman riesgos del mismo nivel. ¿Existen otras causas subyacentes o no intencionales
driving them to risk-taking? Well, this is exactly what I decided to research. So, I founded my research on the basis of a psychological process known as "habituation," or simply what we refer to as "getting used to it." Habituation explains how our brains adapt to some behaviors, like lying, with repeated exposures. And this concept inspired me to design a project to determine if the same principle could be applied to the relentless rise of risk-taking in teenagers. So I predicted that habituation to risk-taking may have the potential to change the already-vulnerable teenage brain by blunting or even eradicating the negative emotions associated with risk, like fear or guilt. I also thought because they would feel less fearful and guilty, this desensitization would lead them to even more risk-taking.
que los lleve a correr riesgos? Esto es exactamente lo que decidí investigar. Basé mi investigación en el proceso psicológico conocido como "habituación", o más conocido como "acostumbrarse". La habituación explica cómo el cerebro se adapta a algunas conductas, a las que se expone repetidamente, como mentir. Este concepto me inspiró a diseñar un proyecto que determinara si se puede aplicar el mismo principio al imparable aumento de riesgos que corren los adolescentes. Predije que la habituación a correr riesgos puede, potencialmente, cambiar el cerebro ya vulnerable del adolescente atenuando, o incluso, eliminando las emociones negativas asociadas con los riesgos, como el miedo o la culpa. También pensé que, al sentir menos miedo y culpa, la insensibilización los llevaría a correr más riesgos.
In short, I wanted to conduct a research study to answer one big question: Why do teens keep making outrageous choices that are harmful to their health and well-being? But there was one big obstacle in my way. To investigate this problem, I needed teenagers to experiment on, laboratories and devices to measure their brain activity, and teachers or professors to supervise me and guide me along the way. I needed resources. But, you see, I attended a high school in South Dakota with limited opportunity for scientific exploration. My school had athletics, band, choir, debate and other clubs, but there were no STEM programs or research mentors. And the notion of high schoolers doing research or participating in a science fair was completely foreign. Simply put, I didn't exactly have the ingredients to make a chef-worthy dish.
En resumen, quería hacer una investigación para responder una gran pregunta: ¿por qué los adolescentes corren riesgos tan grandes que son perjudiciales para su salud y bienestar? Pero había un gran obstáculo en mi camino. Para estudiar este problema, necesitaba adolescentes en los que experimentar, laboratorios, dispositivos para medir la actividad cerebral y profesores que me supervisaran y me guiaran durante el proceso. Necesitaba recursos. Pero estudié en una secundaria de Dakota del Sur con escasas posibilidades para la investigación científica. En la secundaria había atletismo, banda, coro, debate y otros clubes, pero no había programas de CTIM o mentores para investigaciones. Y la idea de que los estudiantes investigaran o participaran en una feria de ciencias era impensable. Simplemente, no tenía los ingredientes para hacer un plato digno de un chef.
And these obstacles were frustrating, but I was also a stubborn teenager. And as the daughter of Bangladeshi immigrants and one of just a handful of Muslim students in my high school in South Dakota, I often struggled to fit in. And I wanted to be someone with something to contribute to society, not just be deemed the scarf-wearing brown girl who was an anomaly in my homogenous hometown. I hoped that by doing this research, I could establish this and how valuable scientific exploration could be for kids like me who didn't necessarily find their niche elsewhere. So with limited research opportunities, inventiveness allowed me to overcome seemingly impossible obstacles. I became more creative in working with a variety of methodologies, materials and subjects. I transformed my unassuming school library into a laboratory and my peers into lab rats. (Laughter) My enthusiastic geography teacher, who also happens to be my school's football coach, ended up as my cheerleader, becoming my mentor to sign necessary paperwork. And when it became logistically impossible to use a laboratory electroencephalography, or EEG, which are those electrode devices used to measure emotional responses, I bought a portable EEG headset with my own money, instead of buying the new iPhone X that a lot of kids my age were saving up for. So finally I started the research with 86 students, ages 13 to 18, from my high school. Using the computer cubicles in my school library, I had them complete a computerized decision-making simulation to measure their risk-taking behaviors comparable to ones in the real world, like alcohol use, drug use and gambling. Wearing the EEG headset, the students completed the test 12 times over three days to mimic repeated risk exposures. A control panel on the EEG headset measured their various emotional responses: like attention, interest, excitement, frustration,
Estos obstáculos eran frustrantes, pero yo era una adolescente terca. Y como hija de inmigrantes de Bangladesh y una de los tantos estudiantes musulmanes en mi secundaria de Dakota del Sur, muchas veces luchaba por encajar. Y quería ser alguien que pudiera contribuir con algo a la comunidad, no ser tan solo la chica morena que usaba un pañuelo y que era una anomalía en mi homogénea ciudad natal. Esperaba que, con la investigación, pudiera establecer esto y la importancia de la investigación científica para jóvenes como yo que no encontraban su lugar en otro sitio. Con unas oportunidades de investigación tan limitadas, la creatividad me permitió superar obstáculos aparentemente imposibles. Me volví más creativa para trabajar con varias metodologías, materiales y sujetos. Transformé la modesta biblioteca de la secundaria en un laboratorio y a mis compañeros, en ratas de laboratorio. (Risas) El entusiasta profesor de geografía, que también es el entrenador del equipo de fútbol, terminó siendo quien me animaba, y luego se convirtió en mi mentor para firmar el papeleo necesario. Y cuando fue logísticamente imposible usar un electroencefalograma de laboratorio, o EEG, que son esos dispositivos con electrodos usados para medir la respuesta emocional, compré un casco EEG portátil con mi propio dinero, en vez de comprarme el iPhone X, para lo que ahorraban muchos de los de mi edad. Finalmente, comencé la investigación con 86 estudiantes de mi secundaria de entre 13 y 18 años. En la biblioteca, usé los cubículos de las computadoras, donde completaron una simulación de toma de decisiones computarizada para medir su conducta de toma de riesgos comparable con las del mundo real, como el exceso de alcohol, el consumo de drogas y las apuestas. Los estudiantes usaron el casco EEG para completar el test 12 veces durante 3 días para imitar las repetidas exposiciones al riesgo. Un panel de control en el casco EEG midió las diferentes respuestas emocionales, como la atención, el interés, el entusiasmo, la frustración,
guilt, stress levels and relaxation. They also rated their emotions on well-validated emotion-measuring scales. This meant that I had measured the process of habituation and its effects on decision-making. And it took 29 days to complete this research. And with months of frantically drafting proposals, meticulously computing data in a caffeinated daze at 2am, I was able to finalize my results. And the results showed that habituation to risk-taking could actually change a teen's brain by altering their emotional levels, causing greater risk-taking. The students' emotions that were normally associated with risks, like fear, stress, guilt and nervousness, as well as attention, were high when they were first exposed to the risk simulator. This curbed their temptations and enforced self-control, which prevented them from taking more risks. However, the more they were exposed to the risks through the simulator, the less fearful, guilty and stressed they became. This caused a situation in which they were no longer able to feel the brain's natural fear and caution instincts. And also, because they are teenagers and their brains are still underdeveloped, they became more interested and excited in thrill-seeking behaviors. So what were the consequences? They lacked self-control for logical decision-making, took greater risks and made more harmful choices. So the developing brain alone isn't to blame. The process of habituation also plays a key role in risk-taking and risk escalation. Although a teen's willingness to seek risk is largely a result of the structural and functional changes associated with their developing brains, the dangerous part that my research was able to highlight was that a habituation to risks can actually physically change a teen's brain and cause greater risk-taking. So it's the combination of the immature teen brain and the impact of habituation that is like a perfect storm to create more damaging effects. And this research can help parents and the general public understand that teens aren't just willfully ignoring warnings or simply defying parents by engaging in increasingly more dangerous behavior. The biggest hurdle they're facing is their habituation to risks: all the physical, detectable and emotional functional changes that drive and control and influence their over-the-top risk-taking. So yes, we need policies that provide safer environments and limit exposures to high risks, but we also need policies that reflect this insight. These results are a wake-up call for teens, too. It shows them that the natural and necessary fear and guilt
la culpa, los niveles de estrés y la relajación. También valoraron sus emociones basados en escalas validadas para medir emociones. Esto significó que había medido el proceso de la habituación y sus efectos en la toma de decisiones. La investigación se completó en 29 días. Y luego de meses de redactar propuestas frenéticamente, computando datos meticulosamente en un aturdimiento por cafeína a las 2 a.m., fui capaz de obtener mis resultados. Y los resultados mostraron que la habituación a correr riesgos podía cambiar el cerebro de un adolescente al alterar sus niveles emocionales, causando así que tomara más riesgos. Las emociones de los estudiantes, generalmente asociadas con los riesgos, como el miedo, el estrés, la culpa y el nerviosismo, así como la atención, eran altas cuando se expusieron por primera vez al simulador. Esto limitó sus tentaciones e impulsó el autocontrol, lo que evitó que corrieran más riesgos. Pero mientras más se exponían a los riesgos por medio del simulador, sentían menos miedo, culpa y estrés. Esto generó una situación en la que ya no eran capaces de sentir los instintos naturales del cerebro de miedo y precaución. Y como son adolescentes y sus cerebros no se han terminado de desarrollar, las conductas que buscan emoción les interesan y entusiasman más. ¿Cuáles son las consecuencias? No tenían autocontrol para tomar decisiones de manera lógica, corrían mayores riesgos y tomaban más decisiones perjudiciales. Así que no podemos culpar solo al cerebro en desarrollo. El proceso de habituación también juega un rol importante en la toma de riesgos y en la escalada de riesgo. Aunque el deseo de riesgo que tienen los jóvenes es, en gran parte, el resultado de los cambios estructurales y funcionales asociados con el cerebro en desarrollo, la parte peligrosa que pude resaltar con la investigación es que la habituación a los riesgos realmente puede cambiar físicamente el cerebro del joven y hacer que corra más riesgos. Entonces, es la combinación del cerebro adolescente inmaduro y el impacto de la habituación lo que genera la tormenta perfecta para crear efectos más perjudiciales. Esta investigación puede ayudar a que los padres y el público en general entiendan que los adolescentes no ignoran las advertencias voluntariamente o desafían a los padres adoptando conductas cada vez más peligrosas. El mayor obstáculo que enfrentan es la habituación a los riesgos: todos los cambios funcionales físicos, detectables y emocionales que conducen, controlan e influencian su deseo desmesurado de correr riesgos. Así que sí, necesitamos políticas que ofrezcan ambientes más seguros y limiten la exposición a altos riesgos. Pero también necesitamos políticas que reflejen esta percepción. Estos resultados también son un llamado de atención a los jóvenes. Les muestra que el miedo y la culpa, necesarios y naturales,
that protect them from unsafe situations actually become numb when they repeatedly choose risky behaviors. So with this hope to share my findings with fellow teenagers and scientists, I took my research to the Intel International Science and Engineering Fair, or ISEF, a culmination of over 1,800 students
que los protegen de situaciones peligrosas se adormecen cuando eligen conductas riesgosas repetidamente. Con la idea de compartir estos resultados con otros adolescentes y científicos, llevé mi investigación a la Feria Internacional de Ciencia e Ingeniería de Intel o ISEF, una cumbre de más de 1800 estudiantes
from 75 countries, regions and territories, who showcase their cutting-edge research and inventions. It's like the Olympics of science fair. (Laughter) There, I was able to present my research to experts in neuroscience and psychology and garner valuable feedback. But perhaps the most memorable moment of the week was when the booming speakers suddenly uttered my name
de 75 países, regiones y territorios, que exhiben sus innovadoras investigaciones e inventos. Es como las Olimpíadas de la feria de ciencias. (Risas) Allí pude presentar mi investigación a expertos en neurociencia y psicología y obtener comentarios valiosos. Pero quizás el mejor momento de la semana fue cuando los resonantes altavoces, de repente, dijeron mi nombre
during the awards ceremony. I was in such disbelief that I questioned myself: Was this just another "La La Land" blunder like at the Oscars? (Laughter) Luckily, it wasn't. I really had won first place in the category "Behavioral and Social Sciences." (Applause) Needless to say, I was not only thrilled to have this recognition, but also the whole experience of science fair that validated my efforts keeps my curiosity alive and strengthens my creativity, perseverance and imagination. This still image of me experimenting in my school library may seem ordinary, but to me, it represents a sort of inspiration. It reminds me that this process taught me to take risks. And I know that might sound incredibly ironic. But I took risks realizing that unforeseen opportunities often come from risk-taking -- not the hazardous, negative type that I studied, but the good ones, the positive risks. The more risks I took,
durante la ceremonia de premios. Tal era mi incredulidad que me pregunté si no era otra metida de pata como la de "La La Land" en los Oscar. (Risas) Afortunadamente, no lo era. De verdad había ganado el primer puesto en la categoría "Ciencias Sociales y de la Conducta" (Aplausos) Demás está decir que no solo estaba emocionada por este reconocimiento, sino también por la experiencia de que la feria de ciencias reconozca mi esfuerzo mantenga viva mi curiosidad, y fortalezca mi creatividad, perseverancia e imaginación. Aunque esta imagen de estar experimentando en la biblioteca de la secundaria pueda parecer normal, para mí representa una especie de inspiración. Me recuerda que este proceso me enseñó a correr riesgos. Y sé que eso puede sonar increíblemente irónico. Pero corrí riesgos y me di cuenta de que las oportunidades inesperadas suelen aparecer al correr riesgos, no de los peligrosos o negativos que estudié, pero los riesgos buenos, los positivos. Cuanto más riesgos tomé,
the more capable I felt of withstanding my unconventional circumstances, leading to more tolerance, resilience and patience for completing my project. And these lessons have led me to new ideas like: Is the opposite of negative risk-taking also true? Can positive risk-taking escalate with repeated exposures? Does positive action build positive brain functioning? I think I just might have my next research idea. (Applause)
más capaz me sentí de tolerar mis circunstancias poco convencionales. Eso me ayudó a ser más tolerante, resiliente y paciente para completar mi proyecto. Y estas lecciones me llevaron a nuevas ideas como: lo opuesto a correr riesgos negativos ¿también es cierto? ¿Correr riesgos positivos puede escalar con las exposiciones repetidas? ¿La acción positiva genera un funcionamiento cerebral positivo? Creo que ya tengo la idea para mi próxima investigación. (Aplausos)